Hello everyone. In this video, we will perform UT using Cantata.
First, we will have a list of modules that need to be tested using Cantata.
In this video, we will perform UT for the first module.
Before performing UT using Cantata, we will be provided with the database files.
In this database, there will be a header folder.
It contains all the header files used in the C file.
Besides that, it also contains all Cantata folders for each module.
So when we need to perform Cantata testing,
we only need to copy the header file and the corresponding Cantata file for the C file we need to test.
For example, in this video, I will perform UT for UT008, so I will copy the header file and the UT008 file into my workspace.
After copying them into my workspace, I will open Cantata.
After opening the Cantata interface, we will switch it to C/C++ mode.
After that, we will open the header folder and the UT folder that we need to work on.
Cantata is a release folder, but we can delete it and perform it again.
First, I will perform the release step.
I will select the C file that I need to perform.
Then I will select Release.
When the console window shows the line containing WinMan@16,
it means that the release step has completed successfully.
Now I can create a test case for this C file.
I can copy the C file name, then simulate test script.
For the coverage rule, I will select
Report All Methods.
At this point, Cantata will report all coverage metrics such as C0, C1, and MCDC.
After that,
I will select Finish.
Then I will select test case.
At this point, Cantata has not created any Test case for us yet.
So I will create a test case for this module.
Here, I will create a test case for the first function.
Copy the Function. Then select it.
This is a sample test case, and it will contain the test case name.
This is where we assign values to global variables, input variables, and expected values.
This is also where we assign values to the global variables after calculation.
Next is the test case description section.
Here, when I cover any section, I can add comments here.
Next is the expected calls section.
For UT, we only set the source code for a single C module.
Therefore, some functions may be implemented in other modules.
Here, I will perform stub for those functions.
I will not run the actual code of the other functions.
Here, it will include all of them.
Next, this is the function that we are calling to.
Finally is the check function,
which will check all global variables
declared in the C file,
including static variables.
This function returns a value.
For this function, we can
perform stub on it.
The stubbing work will be done below the test case
We can search for the function.
This function will return a value of 8-bit signed interger.
So we will consider this condition,
this condition is TRUE when the return value of this following function is 1.
So I can stub the value and give it a name that I can call later.
So that when I call it by function, it will return the value 1.
At this point, when Cantata reads this function,
it will understand that the return value of this function is 1.
At the same time, we can also set the variables returned by this function.
For example, I can set the value returned by this function by 0.
With this condition setup, I have covered the true case of this condition.
After the true case, the code will continue to this line.
It will meet another return function.
This return function has an enum type.
So I can create a stub return value for it in the same way (enum type).
I can also copy its name.
Next is the static variable
It will be assigned using the return value of the helper function.
Here, we can also stub its return value.
This is a boolean function to stub its return value into TRUE or FALSE
In this case, I can assign its return value as TRUE.
This is similar to the previous stub configurations.
This function has a boolean return type.
So we can stub its return value as either TRUE or FALSE.
So in this case I need to cover the TRUE case of this function,
I will set its return value to TRUE.
Next is the value of this static variable
which is again assigned using the return value of this function.
Similarly, I will stub the return value for it.
Here, I have assigned this variable to true.
The value of this variable was also assigned to true earlier.
So it will enter the true case of this condition.
At this point, when it enters the true case of the condition,
it will call this function.
This function is a void function, so I do not need a return value.
I only need to check if it is called.
The value of this variable will then be assigned to the negated return value of this function.
This function is also a boolean function.
So its return value will be either TRUE or FALSE.
Here, its value is true.
Since the return value of this function is false, the condition below is also satisfied.
This also means that this function will be called.
Next, as the logic entered the true branch, it won't enter the false branch.
So I skip this false function right here,
and finally in this function, a call for this function will be perform.
As this function has only 1 variable,
we can assign a value to it
by setting the value of the variable in the stub section.
Here, I will give it a name.
Here, I can add a comment saying that
I will cover
the true case of this condition.
After that, for all inputs
of the functions
and the test case comments,
as well as their return variables,
first, this variable will return the value assigned from the return value of this stub function.
Earlier, I already configured its return value to be 1,
so here I will expect it to be this value, which means 1.
Similarly, this is a static variable,
I will also set a clear value for it.
This static variable is assigned here,
and also assigned here.
So I will take its latest assigned value.
Since I set the return value of this stub to TRUE,
that means the value of this variable after assignment
will be the negation of TRUE,
so it will be false.
Next is the test interrupted variable
This variable will receive the return value of this function.
Earlier, I set the return value of this function to TRUE.
So the returned value of this variable will also be TRUE.
Finally, the return value of this variable,
when this function is called,
it will be assigned
using the value returned by the stub function.
Earlier, I set its value to one.
So at this point, the return value of this variable will also be one.
So all static variables
and normal global variables
have had their expected values checked.
Now I can run my test case to see whether the result is as expected.
I will select Run,
select the input module,
and select the test case.
Here, I will run it.
In the console window, I can check that all of my check lines
check that all of my check lines have passed.
This means that the expected values and the actual values match.
Besides that, I can also view which conditions my testcase has covered using Code Coverage Viewer.
Here, according to my comment, I expect to cover the true case of this condition.
Now, in Code Coverage Viewer, it also shows that I have entered the true case.
Next is the code coverage result, I can also check here,
where it shows the total C0, C1, and MCDC coverage metrics.
If the result meets my testing purpose, I will continue creating testcases for the entire function in the same way.
The first function is a set of testcases, and the second function will also have its own set of testcases.
Now I will run it again one more time.
As you can see here, in Code Coverage Viewer, all of my conditions have been covered.
In Code Coverage Viewer, all metrics have also reached 100%.
At this point, I have completed all UT tasks for this module.
I will select my module
to generate the report.
In this report, it will also show my coverage metrics, such as
C0, C1 and MCDC which are 100%.
Now I can close my Cantata folder.
If I need to perform UT for another module,
I can continue from here.
I can also check the result after performing UT
in the Cantata folder,
in the Result,
then Test Report.
Here, it will show
the overview for this module.
We can summarize that the test result is Pass or Fail.
Here, the result is Pass, The coverage is 100%.
Below this section, there is also a test report for each test case.
Next is the Test Summary.
Here, the Overall Result is also Pass.
And all of my coverage metrics are also 100%.
At this point, I have completed the UT implementation using Cantata for this module.
Thank you for watching.